Guide to the David Price Papers, 1960-2006 and undated RL.01048
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David Price papers
1960-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Price, David Eugene
RL.01048
172.5 Linear Feet
David Price is a political science professor at Duke University, and Democratic congressman from North Carolina's Fourth District since 1987 (re-elected in 2006). The David Price Papers (1960-2006) document the scholarly and political career of David Eugene Price, including his days as a graduate student in the 1960s, his tenure as a political science professor and Democratic Party staff member, and, finally, his years as a Democratic congressman from North Carolina's Fourth District. Records from Price's political headquarters contain thousands of original documents, handwritten and computer-generated; printed materials such as legislative bills and campaign publicity; and a variety of audiovisual materials, including photographs, some slides, many videos, and audio recordings. The collection is especially rich for researchers interested in the American political party system, the work and life of legislators, North Carolina history and government, the North Carolina Democratic and Republican parties, the U.S. Congress, its committee structure, the Hunt Commission, and the broader legislative process. Other materials document political campaigns, notably David Price's own congressional campaigns and Albert Gore's senatorial campaign of 1970-1971.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Congressional papers from 1987-present are restricted. Permission from Representative David Price is required to access these materials until 10 years after he has left office. In addition, unpublished Congressional committee records are closed for 30 years from the date of their creation.
Provenance
The David Price Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1988 and 1997.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1940 Aug. 17 Born in Johnson City, Tenn. to a high school principal and a teacher.
1957-1959 Studied at Mars Hill College
1959 Morehead Scholar at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
1961 Earned B.A. from UNC-Chapel Hill
1963 Hired as summer intern for Senator Bartlett (D.-Alaska); subsequently worked for several summers as a legislative aide
1964 Received Bachelor of Divinity degree from Yale University. Canvassed for Johnson-Humphrey presidential ticket
1967-1969 Instructor at Yale University
1968 Married Lisa Kanwit
1969 Received Ph.D. in political science from Yale University and obtained faculty appointment there
1970 Organized campus groups and Get-Out-The-Vote operations in Senator Albert Gore's (Sr.) (D.-Tenn.) last reelection campaign
1970-1973 Resident Fellow, Trumbull College at Yale University
1972 Served as a field organizer in Muskie's presidential campaign Dissertation published as Who Makes the Laws? (Schenkman, 1972).
1973- Joined political science faculty at Duke University. Helped launch what later became the Terry Sanford Institute of Public Policy
1975 Published The Commerce Committees: A Study of the House and Senate Commerce Committees
1976 Served as Deputy Campaign Manager for North Carolina, managing two congressional districts in Jimmy Carter's presidential campaign
1978-1979 Served as a Field Associate in the Community Development Block Grant monitoring project, The Brookings Institution
1979-1980 Executive Director of the North Carolina Democratic Party
1981-1982 Staff Director, Democratic Party Commission on Presidential Nomination
1981-1983 Director of Graduate Studies in the Department of Political Science, Duke University
1983-1984 Served as Chairman of the North Carolina Democratic Party
1984 Published Bringing Back the Parties (Congressional Quarterly Press, 1984)
1985 Apr. 13 Announced candidacy for the U.S. House of Representatives from North Carolina's Fourth Congressional District
1986 Nov. 4 Elected to the U.S. House of Representatives (100th Congress)
1987 Sponsored the Home Equity Loan Consumer Protection Act Joined the Democratic Budget Group. Appointed to two subcommittees of the Science Committee: Science, Research, and Technology; and Investigations and Oversight. Appointed to three House committees: Banking and Financial Services (formerly Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs); Science (formerly Science, Space, and Technology); and Small Business.
1988 Left the Small Business Committee Won reelection to the U.S. House of Representatives (101st Congress).
1989 Joined the Democratic Caucus' Committee on Organization, Study, and Review Became co-chair of the Democratic Budget Group. Switched from the Investigations Subcommittee to the Natural Resources, Agriculture Research, and Environment Subcommittee.
1990 Won reelection to the U.S. House of Representatives (102nd Congress) Awarded the American Political Science Association's Hubert H. Humphrey Public Service Award.
1991 Appointed to House Appropriations Committee. Joined Appropriations Subcommittee on Transportation, and Subcommittee on Agriculture and Rural Development. Gave up assignments on House Banking, and Science, Space, and Technology Committees. Appointed At-Large Majority Whip
1992 Passage of a bill first introduced by Price, the Scientific and Advanced-Technology Act of 1992. Won a reelection bid to the U.S. House of Representatives (103rd Congress) Published first edition of The Congressional Experience (Westview Press).
1993 Joined the Budget Committee Left the Appropriations Subcommittee on Agriculture and Rural Development for the Commerce, Justice, State and Judiciary Subcommittee.
1994 Lost reelection campaign to the U.S. House of Representatives (104th Congress).
1995 Returned to faculty position at Duke University
1996 Regained seat in U.S. House of Representatives (105th Congress) for the Fourth District
1997 Received appointment to Appropriations subcommittees VA-HUD, and Treasury, Postal, and General Government. The Price Education Affordability Act was passed Reappointed to House Appropriations Committee.
1998 Reappointed to House Budget Committee Won reelection campaign to U.S. House of Representatives (106th Congress).
1999-2000 Served on Budget Committee Task Force on Natural Resources and the Environment
2000 Reelected to U.S. House of Representatives (107th Congress) Published second edition of The Congressional Experience (Westview Press).
2002 Reelected to U.S. House of Representatives (108th Congress)
2004-2006 Reelected to the U.S. House of Representatives
Price was involved in a number of caucuses, including the Sunbelt Caucus for Members with interests in the southern U.S. For more biographical information, including a list of the many articles Price published, see his curriculum vitae within the collection.
Collection Overview
The David Price Papers document the scholarly and political career of David Eugene Price, including his days as a graduate student in the 1960s, his tenure as a political science professor and Democratic Party staff member, and, finally, his years as a Democratic congressman from North Carolina's Fourth District from 1987 through 1998. Records from Price's political headquarters record the routine activities of Price and his office staff, and the larger system of government in which he participated. The files contain documents, handwritten and computer-generated; printed materials such as legislative bills and campaign publicity; and a variety of audiovisual materials, including photographs, some slides, many videos, and audio recordings. The collection is especially rich for researchers interested in the American political party system, the work and life of legislators, North Carolina history and government, the North Carolina Democratic and Republican Parties, the U.S. Congress, its committee structure, the Hunt Commission, and especially the larger legislative process. Other topics include political campaigns, notably Price's own campaigns and Albert Gore's senatorial campaign of 1970-1971.
Three primary groups comprise the collection. Full descriptions of series and subseries within these groups are found below in the detailed collection description. The Pre-Congressional Papers primarily document Price's years as a student, then as a professor at Yale and Duke Universities; they also trace Price's early involvement with the Democratic Party. These papers are a foundation and prelude to Price's later work as a member of Congress. The Congressional Papers were compiled during his years in public office, and reveal Price's activities as a member of Congress, and his relationships with colleagues, constituents, and other political stakeholders. Finally, the Campaign Office Files were created from the activity of his campaign office in Raleigh, North Carolina, largely separate - as required by law - from the work of his congressional office.
Processing Note
Most original folders and folder titles have been retained. Labels included many abbreviations, acronyms, and initials; the full versions were added in brackets whenever possible. "DP" in folder titles and elsewhere usually refers to "David Price" but can also mean "Democratic Party." Keyword searching is possible within the container list, with some important limitations. First, the expanded forms of acronyms and abbreviations were not added in every instance but rather at the first occurrence with a new series or subseries. Second, labels are not standardized. For example, the search "breast cancer" might retrieve some folders, but not the one labeled "Cancer--breast." A search for the EPA's "Southern Appalachian Mountains Air Quality Initiative" within this collection may not retrieve folders labeled only as "Southern Appalachian Air Quality." To be comprehensive, therefore, searches need to be formulated in several ways. Please consult with a Research Services staff when using this collection.
Dates were obtained by sampling within folders and so may not be strictly accurate. Sampling was also used to identify the content of audiovisual materials, therefore descriptions for recordings may not be complete.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Video recordings; Photographs; Sound recordings; Politicians -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Legislative hearings -- United States; Bills, Legislative; Political parties -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Legislators -- United States -- Archives; North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Political campaigns; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- History -- 20th century; Democratic Party (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; United States. Congress. House; Elections -- North Carolina -- 20th century; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Budget; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Appropriations; United States. Congress. Senate; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Hunt, James B., 1937-; Hunt Commission; Gore, Albert, 1907-1998; Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Price, David Eugene
- Pre-Congressional Papers Record Group, 1960-1988 and undated, bulk 1970-1986
  Scope and Contents note
  These files document the bulk of David Price's academic career prior to his entry into elective office, and reveal the formation of Price's intellectual interest in politics and political parties. Beginning in the mid-1960s during his time as a graduate student at Yale University, they continue through his years on the faculties of Yale and Duke, and end in 1988 during his first term in Congress. The materials are divided into three series, all described further below: Political Party Files; Correspondence and Administrative Files; and Research and Writings. Within each series, the folders are arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  - Political Party Files Series, 1960-1986 and undated, 13 boxes
    Documents Price's close observance of, employment with, and research on the Republican and Democratic political parties, from his graduate work at Yale up to the time he was first elected to Congress. During much of this period Price was serving as a professor of political science at Yale and Duke Universities. Concurrently he also worked for the North Carolina State Democratic Party in various capacities, serving as executive director and as state party chair, and for the national party as director of the Hunt Commission (Commission on Presidential Nominations). The files illustrate the inter-relationship of Price's political work and research. Many of the topical folders contain Price's notes, often related to his writings, as well as articles and documents written by others. Background files for his book on American political parties, Bringing Back the Parties, can be found in this series. As in other parts of the collection, Price's relationships with other prominent political figures are documented here, especially with Jim Hunt, North Carolina governor and head of the Hunt Commission. Correspondence, Hunt Commission documents and meeting transcripts, and a file on Jim Hunt's Senate race against Jesse Helms are included. Other files relate to talks Price gave as a state party leader and include the speeches themselves or Price's notes. There are also files on conferences attended, polling information, and numerous files on Democratic campaigns such as Hunt-Helms (U.S. Senate, 1984), Muskie (U.S. Presidency, 1972), Carter (U.S. Presidency, 1980), and Albert Gore, Sr. (U.S. Senate, 1970).
    The files are arranged roughly in alphabetical order by title.
    See also the Research and Writings Series for further documentation of Price's research interests.
    - 1980 Election-Issues, Commentary, 1980 (Box PCP-1)
    - 1980 Jim Hunt-Political, 1979-1982, 2 folders (Box PCP-1)
    - 1980 Races-Returns, Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box PCP-1)
    - 1982 Elections, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-1)
    - 1984 Issues, 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box PCP-1)
    - 1984 Races-N.C., 1982-1983 and undated (Box PCP-1)
    - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations, 1984 (Box PCP-1)
    - The American Assembly-The Future of American Political Parties, Conference, 1982 (Box PCP-1)
    - American Politics-Elections, 1970-1985 (Box PCP-1)
    - Articles and Primaries, 1976-1983 (Box PCP-2)
    - Articles-Party Conventions, 1960-1984, 3 folders (Box PCP-2)
    - Bringing Back the Parties-- Reviews, Notes, Data, 1981-1986 (Box PCP-2)
    - Bringing Back the Parties, Transcript, undated, 1-4 of 5 folders (Box PCP-2)
    - Bringing Back the Parties, Transcript, undated, 5 of 5 folders (Box PCP-3)
    - Britt, Andrews, Other 1982 Races, 1982 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Finance, 1973-1986 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Finance-Data, 1980-1984 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Finance-Legal Issues, 1979-1985 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Memos, 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign of 1984, 1983-1984 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Planning, 1984 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaign Planning, GOTV [Get Out the Vote], 1980-1984 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaigns (1984), 1982-1984 (Box PCP-3)
    - Campaigns-Miscellaneous, 1976-1984 (Box PCP-4)
    - Carter (1976)- Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box PCP-4)
    - Carter Nomination, 1979-1980 (Box PCP-4)
    - Chairman's Memos, 1983-1984 (Box PCP-4)
    - Congressional Campaign Committees, 1982-1983 (Box PCP-4)
    - Congressional Reform-Bolling Committee, 1974, 2 folders (Box PCP-4)
    - County Democratic Parties
      - Caswell, Person, Granville, and Franklin Counties, 1976 (Box PCP-4)
      - Chatham, Orange, Randolph, 1976-1981 (Box PCP-4)
      - Durham (1976-1980), 1976-1981 (Box PCP-4)
      - Vance, Halifax, and Warren Counties, 1976 and undated (Box PCP-4)
      - Wake (1976, 1980), 1976-1978 (Box PCP-4)
    - DCCC [Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee]-Post Election Survey in Eight Selected Congressional Districts, 1980 Dec. (Box PCP-4)
    - Democratic National Committee (DNC) (Box PCP-5)
      - DNC, 1984-1985 (Box PCP-5)
      - Chairmanship, 1984-1985 (Box PCP-5)
      - Commission on Presidential Nomination, 1981-1982 and undated, 3 folders (Box PCP-5)
      - Commission Reports, 1969-1978 (Box PCP-5)
      - General, 1980-1983 (Box PCP-5)
    - Democratic National Committee (DNC) (Box PCP-6)
      - Hunt Commission
        - Alternative or Supplementary Language, 1982 (Box PCP-6)
        - Background, 1981 (Box PCP-6)
        - Charter Revisions, 1982 (Box PCP-6)
        - Data, Staff Documents, 1981-1983 (Box PCP-6)
        - Implementation, CRC, 1982-1984 (Box PCP-6)
        - Memos, Speeches, 1981-1985 (Box PCP-6)
        - Miscellaneous Notes, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-6)
        - DNC-Hunt Commission-Press, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-6)
        - Rules-Their Effect, 1984-1985 (Box PCP-6)
        - Transcripts, 1981 Nov., 2 folders (Box PCP-6)
        - Transcripts, 1982 Jan., 3 folders (Box PCP-6)
    - Democratic National Committee (DNC) (Box PCP-7)
      - Hunt Commission
        - Transcripts, 1982 Jan. [partial], 3 folders (Box PCP-7)
        - Transcripts, 1982 Feb. (Box PCP-7)
      - Issues, Strategy Council, 1969-1983, 2 folders (Box PCP-7)
      - Meeting to Approve Commission Reports, 1982 (Box PCP-7)
      - Midterm Conference, 1978-1982 (Box PCP-7)
      - Platform Accountability Commission, 1982-1983 (Box PCP-7)
    - Democratic Future-Post 1984 (Box PCP-8)
    - Democratic Party (1976), 1976 (Box PCP-8)
    - Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee- Consultation Weekend Materials, circa 1984 (Box PCP-8)
    - Duke Forum [on Presidential Nominations], 1981 (Box PCP-8)
    - Edgecombe-Nash, 1976 (Box PCP-8)
    - Election (1984), 1979-1984 (Box PCP-8)
    - Fairness Commission/Presidential Nomination Post, 1984, 1985 (Box PCP-8)
    - Education Materials-Gore Campaign, 1970 (Box PCP-8)
    - Elections, 1970-1982 (Box PCP-8)
    - Finances [State DP], 1984-1985 (Box PCP-8)
    - Gore-Article on Precinct Operations; Memphis and [Lupfer?] Correspondence, 1970 and undated (Box PCP-8)
    - Gore Campaign-Davidson, 1970-1971 and undated (Box PCP-8)
    - Gore Campaign-Knox, 1970-1971 (Box PCP-8)
    - Gore Campaign Literature, 1970 and undated (Box PCP-8)
    - Gore Campaign-Notes and Memoranda, Clippings and Articles, 1970-1972 (Box PCP-9)
    - Gore Campaign-Polls, 1970 (Box PCP-9)
    - Gore Campaign-Ward and Precinct Work, 1970 (Box PCP-9)
    - Helms newspaper ads, 1978-1984 (Box PCP-9)
    - Hunt Campaign (1984), 1983-1984 (Box PCP-9)
    - Institute of Politics, Kennedy School of Government, The Parties and the Nominating Process, Conference, 1981 (Box PCP-9)
    - Issues-Democratic Agenda, 1981-1984, 2 folders (Box PCP-9)
    - Issues, Reagan, 1981-1984 (Box PCP-9)
    - Leland Commission, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-9)
    - Local Parties, 1961-1983 (Box PCP-9)
    - Muskie and McGovern Campaigns, Clippings, Materials, 1971-1972 (Box PCP-9)
    - Muskie N.C. Campaign-Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box PCP-10)
    - National Convention, 1977-1984, 2 folders (Box PCP-10)
    - National Journal, 1984 Apr., July, 2 folders (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - National Party Role, 1980-1985 (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - N.C.-Cambridge Survey Research, 1976 Election Standings, Other N.C. Polls (1980, 1984), 1976-1984, 3 folders (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - NCDP [North Carolina Democratic Party], Current, 1985 (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - NC SDEC- Finances, Memos, 1980-1981 (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - Nomination Process-Articles and Bibliography (General), 1979-1982 (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - Other Candidates and Hunt, 1974-1976 (Oversize-box OVSZ 1)
    - PR Book-Nominations Data, 1970-1980 (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties and Community, undated (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties, etc, DP Talks, 1977-1984 (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties in Government
      - State, 1979-1984 (Box PCP-11)
      - National-Executive Branch, 1978-1983 (Box PCP-11)
      - National-Congress, 1978-1983 (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties in the Electorate, 1978-1983 (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties-Role, Current Health, 1979-1980 (Box PCP-11)
    - Parties-The Normative Argument, 1979-1982 (Box PCP-11)
    - Party- Campaign Finance-Articles, 1975-1983, 3 folders (Box PCP-11)
    - Party-Legal Status, 1979-1985, 1 of 2 folders (Box PCP-11)
    - Party-Legal Status, 1979-1985, 2 of 2 folders (Box PCP-12)
    - Party Reform-Its Consequences, 1977-1985 and undated (Box PCP-12)
    - Party to People, 1984 and undated (Box PCP-12)
    - Platform Accountability, 1980-1984 (Box PCP-12)
    - Precinct Work, undated (Box PCP-12)
    - Price Speaking Engagements, 1979-1985 (Box PCP-12)
    - RNC-Commission Reports, 1967-1984 (Box PCP-12)
    - Reapportionment, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-12)
    - Republican National Committee, 1980-1984 (Box PCP-12)
    - Republican National Committee, Pamphlets, 1978-1980 (Box PCP-12)
    - Republican Party-Issues, 1966-1983 (Box PCP-12)
    - Returns, News Stories, 1976 (Box PCP-12)
    - Rules Commissions-Background and Commentary, 1971-1985 (Box PCP-13)
    - Runoff Primary, 1984 (Box PCP-13)
    - State Law and Parties, 1976-1983, 2 folders (Box PCP-13)
    - State Parties, Plans, 1980-1984, 2 folders (Box PCP-13)
    - Tennessee Politics, Statewide, 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box PCP-13)
  - Correspondence and Administrative Files Series, 1969-1986 and undated, 6 boxes
    Documents various aspects of Price's political and academic careers. Political files illuminate Price's ties to other prominent Democrats and his work on the Democratic Party's behalf, chiefly through correspondence, while academic files concern Price's academic administrative responsibilities, chiefly at Duke University and less often at Yale University; some materials pertain to personal activities such as Price's leave of absence, including fellowship applications, course syllabi, and course evaluations. Other items, such as departmental newsletters and other materials, give a larger picture of Price's academic environment. One file relates to the controversy over whether Duke should host the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library. While correspondence is scattered throughout the Pre-Congressional Papers, this series contains several folders devoted almost entirely to correspondence. These letters to and from Price cover both personal and political topics, with the latter most often about fundraising.
    The series is roughly arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - APSA [American Political Science Association], Professional Affairs, 1974-1985 (Box PCP-13)
    - CDBG [Community Development Block Grant]-General, 1977-1984 (Box PCP-13)
    - CDBG-Current, 1977-1979 (Box PCP-14)
    - CDBG-Final Reports-Raleigh, Durham, 1978-1981, 2 folders (Box PCP-14)
    - Correspondence, Personal/Professional, 1970-1985 (Box PCP-14)
    - Duke Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, 1974-1986, 2 folders (Box PCP-14)
    - Duke Policy News, 1976-1986, 2 folders (Box PCP-14)
    - Duke Political Science Department and General, 1975-1986, 2 folders (Box PCP-14)
    - Duke-recruitment and promotion (Box PCP-15)
    - Duke-Reports and Documents, 1974-1981 and undated (Box PCP-15)
    - Durham-CDBG, 1975-1979, 3 folders (Box PCP-15)
    - England, 1975-1978 (Box PCP-15)
    - Evaluations (Duke and Yale), 1973-1975 and undated (Box PCP-15)
    - Fundraising Letters, 1983-1986 (Box PCP-15)
    - Leave of Absence-Closed, 1970-1975 (Box PCP-15)
    - Nixon Library, 1981-1982 (Box PCP-15)
    - Price-Personal and Press, 1983-1985 (Box PCP-16)
    - Price-Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box PCP-16)
    - Prospectuses and Proposals, 1974-1983, 2 folders (Box PCP-16)
    - Raleigh-CDBG, 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box PCP-16)
    - Research Council, 1975-1985 (Box PCP-16)